This task is about a Petri net and it's a
task about fixing a Petri net.
We have been given the task of fixing the
Petri net for a water gate, the Petriburg water gate.
First of all, we need to understand how the
water gate shall function.
So we have got a river and we have got a lake
and a water gate in between.
Ships are able to go from the river to the
lake by using the water gate.
Ships are only going in one direction and
the river has a higher water level than the
lake.
The water gate can have a high water level
and a low water level.
Gate one can open only if the water level
within the water gate is high, or can only
be open if the water level in the water gate
is high.
Gate two can only be open if the water level
in the water gate is low.
Then ships can go from the river to the water gate
if the gate one is open and from the water gate
to the lake if gate two is open.
Ships can only go into the water gate if there
is no ship in the water gate already.
Furthermore, this process shall continue even
if there was a ship already going through
the water gate.
So it shall not be that the water gate is only
to be used once or twice or something like
this.
So the process should be able to continue.
So for the gates, it shall
be so that the gate is either opened or closed.
It shall be true for gate one and for gate
two.
The water level is either high or low.
So this is all the information that we have
available at each point in time and there are
ships either waiting or not waiting.
So ships can either wait at the river or within
the water gate, but either a ship is waiting
or there is no ship waiting.
So we do not want to have multiple ships in
the water gate.
We've been given a Petri net and this Petri
net is right down here.
There are descriptions for transitions as
well.
So what the transitions within this Petri
net mean.
Then we have got tasks.
The first one is to describe in words everything
that can go wrong with this circuit.
Then we try to find all five errors that may
occur with this Petri net.
We know this Petri net is wrong and this Petri
net has got all these places and transitions.
We shall think of what the description of
the water gate was and then compare to what's
happening actually.
So, how do we find errors?
Well, actually I've created the whole Petri
net within PIPE tool and we can use this one
in order to see what's happening when firing
transitions, or just as a little helper.
But we could also work without drawing it
in PIPE.
This is just a little helper in order to see
actually what's happening.
You may also have a look at the German version,
where this task was approached differently
not using PIPE, if you are interested in it.
So now let's see what we can do here.
So
now
I put this into the foreground so that we
see what we have got in PIPE here, and I moved
this one aside.
Basically it's the same Petri net.
It looks differently in PIPE tool, but it's
the same Petri net.
We have got all the ones at the edges, but
we have the same transitions and we've got
the same places as well.
But what we can do with PIPE is we can actually
see where the tokens are going to without
thinking it through in mind.
I will start doing this now so that we can
see the actual errors that happen.
One error that occurs is concerning the water
level.
So when we fire t8, then we open gate two.
Now at the moment, the water level within
the water gate is low.
So this is good because gate two shall only
be opened if the water level is low.
However, we can set the water level too high.
Now we have got an erroneous state.
I just placed this scenario here so that we
can actually remember it.
So, we fire t8 and then we fire t5, and then
we are landing in this erroneous state, because
now the water level is high and the gate is
open, which was prohibited in our task.
Let's go back and let's consider another situation.
We could fire t5 first, and then we can fire t2,
and we have got gate one open.
Here we have got the same problem because
when we fire t5 and then t2, we can afterwards
fire t6.
When this happens, we have a low water level,
but gate one open, which is not allowed.
So this is a problem as well.
So we have the problem with the water level
at both directions.
What else can happen?
Well, we've got problems with our gates as
well, and this is something which we can see
immediately when we look at the Petri net
here.
Well, I execute what's happening and write
it down right here while doing it.
So we fire t5 and then we fire t2, and now
we can fire t3, and then we can fire t4.
Now we see a problem.
What's happening here?
Well, we fire t4 and our gate is neither open
nor closed.
This is a serious problem because this is
something which was explicitly told that it
should never happen.
It's, furthermore, also obviously a problem
because we have to have any state for the
gate.
It has to be either opened or closed.
So this is a problem.
We've got another problem here.
If we would have fixed this problem, then
we could fire t3 again.
And if we would still have a token here right
in that position, then we could fire t4 again
and we would have another ship in the water gate,
which is obviously a problem.
We see this problem also occurring here because
we have at the moment a token within the
ship-in-watergate-yes, and also within the
ship-in-watergate-no.
So this is a state which should never, ever
occur.
In fact, we could say we have this sequence
here leads to two problems.
So we have the problem that there could be
multiple ships in the water gate, and we have
the problem that gate one
can be neither open nor
closed.
Let's continue with the next problem.
For that, we start with the same sequence.
So we start with t5, t2, t3, and t4.
Well, now we should be able to change the
water level again.
So at this moment, we can't do anything here
with the gate.
So I proceed as we can.
So we could fire t6 at this state.
Then we
can fire t8.
Then we see the problem at the other gate
when we fire t7, because what is happening
now is that we have no token in gate two as
well.
So now we have a problem that we have no
token in either gate-2-open or gate-2-closed.
This is a serious error.
After looking at these problems, we can look
back again to our task, and they say that
we have to find five arrows, which we did,
and now we have to fix the Petri net by adding
the arrows that are missing.
So we have to add seven arrows, it says here,
but we are not allowed to change the transitions
or places.
So it's just adding arrows, which shall lead
to a valid Petri net.
Let's do this within the PIPE tool here.
I will go back to the initial state and stop
the running process.
Now I will add more edges.
So we have to think about the problems that
arose.
We start with the first sequence, firing t8
and t5, which led to the problem that we had
gate two open, but the water level high.
This problem arose because we could fire t5
although gate two was opened, and we can fix
this by adding an edge from the gate two closed
side.
So when we say, when gate two is closed, that
only then we can fire this transition, then
we will not have the problem that we can fire
this transition at all while the gate is open.
So we see this now here, we cannot fire this
transition as this edge requires that there's
a token in here.
So only if we have the token in there we can
fire this transition.
Now we added a new problem.
What happened here?
We have no token in gate two, neither in opened
nor in closed.
Why did this happen?
Well, because now we added this edge, but
we have to add the token back into gate two
closed, because after we fire this transition,
the gate needs to be closed still.
This is something we have not represented yet.
So we can add a transition here that goes
back to the closed state.
So we have one forward and one backward from
the transition so that there's still a token
after firing the transition.
The same problem also happened with gate one.
In this case, we could fire t6 while gate
one was opened.
Again, we can prohibit this by requiring that
we can fire t6 only when gate one is closed.
So we add an edge here that requires that
the gate is closed when firing t6.
Again, we have to add the back edge so that
the gate is still closed after firing t6.
So we add the back edge.
Then we had a problem that the gates could
be opened, or could be led into a state where
they are neither open nor closed.
This was by firing either t4 or t7.
So let's start with t4.
When we fire t4, we remove the token from
gate one.
We just fixed this problem for the water gate.
So maybe let's actually show that this problem
is solved now.
So when we fire t5 now, we still have the
token in there.
So it does not lead to a problem and the same
occurs here.
So we still have a token in closed.
We can fix this problem here.
So I just showed the problem again.
When we fire t4 here, we remove the token.
We can fix this by adding an edge back.
So let's do this.
We add an edge from t4 back to gate one open,
and then- Maybe let's make it clearer.
This is the back edge here so that we actually
can see both edges.
So one edge goes back and the other forward.
So we keep the token in gate one open.
We could have also moved the token into gate
one closed.
This would have been valid as well as nobody
prevents us from directly going to the closed
state for the gate after having a ship enter.
So we are free to choose this one.
There's nothing in the description of the
text preventing it.
The other one that was a similar problem was
transition seven, removing the token from
gate two, and we have the same fix here.
So we add a back edge and now we can fire
this transition as well without losing the
token in gate two.
Then there was the last problem, which also
was entered by firing t4 here, which was that
we could have multiple ships in the water gate,
which can actually arise just now, and we
can also see this problem now.
So when we fire those transitions here, we
can add one ship here and then we can add
a second ship, and a third, and that's just
not allowed.
Because the condition says there shall be
one token either in ship-in-watergate-yes,
or in ship-in-watergate-no.
So, how do we fix this?
Well, we add another precondition for t4 by
adding an edge.
What we require for the water gate is, that when
we want to add a ship into the water gate then
we require that there is no ship in the water gate,
and this is exactly the edge we add.
So from the ship in water gate to transition
four, we add another edge.
When we do this, I’ll maybe move this edge
here like so, then we fix this edge here as
well.
We can check back again.
We have seven edges added, so 1, 2, 3, 4,
5, 6, and 7.
These are the edges that we added.
So now everything should be fixed and we can
also play around now.
So we can just choose randomly some transitions
and we will not get into a state where something
goes wrong.
So we can fire t4 here.
Then we have a ship inside the gate, but we
cannot add another ship into the gate, even
if there are tokens in the ship waiting and
gate one open.
Only when we close the gate again
and then set the water level to low, then
we can let the ship leave.
Then we can have another ship enter the water gate.
We can start even with our sequences and see
that no problems arise.
So we can fire t8 and then afterwards we can
see that we cannot fire t5 now.
So we see this sequence is not possible anymore.
This fixes our first problem.
Then when we fire t5, and then we fire t2,
we cannot fire t6.
So the second problem is solved as well.
When we fire t5, and then we fire t2, and
then we fire t3, and then we fire t4, we had
two problems.
One was that we had the gate with no token
left, gate one.
Now we have a token still in gate one, and
we have only one token for the ship in the
water gate.
So we remove two errors here and we can check
the last of our errors as well.
So we fire t5 and t2, and then we fire t3
and t4.
Now we have a token right in here. We
cannot fire t6 right on.
We first have to close the gate.
This is what changed because of the other
error that we had with the water level.
So we fire t1, and then we can fire t6 and
t8, and now we can fire t7, and still there's
a token in gate two.
So now everything works fine and we can check
this with the PIPE tool or see actually what
happens when we use the PIPE tool.
Now we are done with this task and I hope
it helped to actually see what's happening
with the Petri net using the PIPE tool here.